Brian David Kiehl

Top Secret SCI (w/ CI Poly)

Summary

Brian is a highly accomplished technical leader with over fifteen years of cyber security experience in both the military and civilian realms. Currently recalled to active duty as an instructor of cyber operations at the United States Naval Academy, he provides a combination of technical and theoretical instruction in all aspects of information assurance and cyber security. In addition to his teaching duties, he manages outreach projects for the USNA Cyber Center and mentors graduating Information Professional and Cyber Warfare Officers.

In his civilian career, Brian has held senior information security engineer positions with the Defense Information Systems Agency (DISA), Lockheed Martin Corporation, and SafeNet, Inc.

Education

Master of Science in Information Assurance | Johns Hopkins University | May 2006 Bachelor of Science in Computer Science | Shepherd University | May 2003

Training & Certifications

- ISC² Certified Information Systems Security Professional (CISSP #359348)
- EC-Council Certified Ethical Hacker (CEH #03409049817)
- SANS SEC560 Network Penetration Testing & Ethical Hacking
- National Security Telecommunications and Information Systems Security (NSTISSI 4011)

Professional Experience

United States Naval Academy

Cyber Science Department - Annapolis, Maryland

July 2018 - Present July 2013 - July 2016

Cyber Instructor

- Course Coordinator for SY110 Intro to Cyber Security managed the core cyber security course that is required by all students at USNA. Led the team of 30 faculty members that delivered the course to over 500 students during the spring 2015 semester. Developed new course curriculum and assisted in the management of the web/linux/virtual infrastructure utilized by faculty & students.
- Provided a combination of technical and academic instruction to 600+ students on all aspects of cyber security, to include: Architecture &Operating Systems, Client/Server Hardening, Web Vulnerabilities, Injection Attacks, Networking, Encryption/Digital Crypto, and Network Recon & Attack.

- Managed/Coordinated the USNA Cyber Center Lecture Series, a recurring series of cyber-related lectures from flag-level military officers and industry leaders, attended by over 1200 students & faculty members.
- Served as the senior Information Professional (IP) Officer at USNA. Conducted IP Officer service selection boards and mentored those selected until their report date at their first duty command.

Defense Information Systems AgencyAugust 2016 - July 2018 DISA Command Center - Fort Meade, Maryland October 2012 - July 2013

Cyber Intel Analyst (2016-2018)

- Lead the planning, coordination, implementation, validation, mitigation and compliance of cyber security tasks.
- Establish and lead Operational Planning Teams (OPT) in order to plan and execute DISA Cyber Missions.
- Issue orders in support of Defensive Cyber Operations (DCO) of the DoD Information Network (DODIN).
- Coordinate with mission partners to help shape DISA Network Assurance strategic alignment.
- Establish subordinate command reporting portals and provide status reporting to senior commanders.
- Serve as a Cyber Security Watch Officer and/or Special Projects Team Lead as required.

Principal Cyber Security Engineer (2012-2013)

- Monitored the Defense Information Systems Network (DISN) to identify computer incidents, provide threat analysis and proactive response, and disseminate threat/incident reports.
- Analyzed results of Intrusion Assessments (i.e. Penetration Testing) to incorporate into DISA Defensive Cyber Operations (DCO) corrective actions and/or future mitigation strategies.
- Managed and coordinated DISA's Host Based Security System (HBSS) command and control operations. Configured and tuned global HBSS ePO reporting server. Identified and alerted on HBSS events.
- Briefed senior leadership on existing security posture and defensive cyber recommendations.

SafeNet, Inc.

December 2010 - July 2012

Corporate Headquarters, Belcamp, MD

Lead Information Security Engineer

- Managed the company's enterprise technical security solutions: global system patching, enterprise anti-virus, internal & external vulnerability scanning, and log management & correlation.
- Designated Information Systems Security Manager (ISSM) for SafeNet's cleared DoD spaces.
- Managed the company's LogRhythm SIEM log correlation system for alerting and forensic analysis.
- Developed the company's internal security policies, directives and standards (NIST/DoD).
- Developed and delivered information security awareness training program to SafeNet employees.

Lockheed Martin Corporation March 2004 - December 2010

Corporate Information Security Team, Bethesda, MD

Information Assurance Engineer

- Conducted network architecture vulnerability analysis for Lockheed Martin's extranet environments.
- Assessed overall compliance with both corporate and federal policies and procedures.
- Designated Approver (DA) for external network connections to the Lockheed Martin intranet.
- Successfully balanced risk management and mission requirements while making final determinations.
- Conducted risk/vulnerability assessments and security audits, and implemented resulting mitigations.

US Navy Reserves

Defense Intelligence Agency | Lieutenant | 2016-2018 Washington, DC

- Executive Officer Unit second-in-command, responsible for unit administration and operational readiness.
- Supervised unit members in daily operations, logistics, and maintenance of DIA IT/IA network systems.

Naval Criminal Investigative Service | Lieutenant | 2011-2013 Quantico, VA

• Cyber Division Officer-Provide Cyber Intelligence Analysis support for target investigations.

Naval Network Warfare Command | Ensign | 2008-2011 Norfolk, VA

- Provided Information Security/Assurance expertise in support of the NETWARCOM mission.
- Terminal Fury Exercise 2011 Observing, recording and reporting network attack and defense activities.

Applications | Environments | Frameworks

Windows/Linux (Kali), Snort, Nessus, McAfee ePO, NeXpose, LogRhythm,, WireShark, NMAP, Cascade Server Web Management System, DoD Risk Management Framework (RMF/DIACAP), FISMA FIPS 199/200, NIST 800 Series, DISA/NSA Security Technical Implementation Guides (STIGs), Microsoft Office/SharePoint, Continuity of Operations (COOP)